<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Roaring Bitmaps</title>
    <link>http://roaringbitmap.org/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Roaring Bitmaps</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="http://roaringbitmap.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://roaringbitmap.org/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://roaringbitmap.org/about/</guid>
      <description>Bitsets, also called bitmaps, are commonly used as fast data structures. Unfortunately, they can use too much memory. To compensate, we often use compressed bitmaps.
Roaring bitmaps are compressed bitmaps which tend to outperform conventional compressed bitmaps such as WAH, EWAH or Concise. In some instances, they can be hundreds of times faster and they often offer significantly better compression.
 Use Roaring for bitmap compression whenever possible. Do not use other bitmap compression methods (Wang et al.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://roaringbitmap.org/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://roaringbitmap.org/publications/</guid>
      <description>Academic Publications by the Roaring Developers  Samy Chambi, Daniel Lemire, Owen Kaser, Robert Godin, Better bitmap performance with Roaring bitmaps, Software: Practice and Experience 46 (5), pages 709-719, May 2016. arXiv:1402.6407. (Data used in the paper) Daniel Lemire, Gregory Ssi-Yan-Kai, Owen Kaser, Consistently faster and smaller compressed bitmaps with Roaring, Software: Practice and Experience 46 (11), pages 1547-1569, November 2016. arXiv:1603.06549 Samy Chambi, Daniel Lemire, Robert Godin, Kamel Boukhalfa, Charles Allen, Fangjin Yang, Optimizing Druid with Roaring bitmaps, IDEAS 2016, 2016.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software</title>
      <link>http://roaringbitmap.org/software/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://roaringbitmap.org/software/</guid>
      <description>We have a Roaring Bitmap organization on GitHub counting over 40 programmers. We maintain a portable format specification.
 RoaringBitmap is a widely used, optimized and robust Java library. It supports both regular and off-heap (e.g., memory mapped) bitmaps. The CRoaring library is a C/C++ library that provides an optimized implementation of Roaring for C/C++ programmers. It works under Windows (Visual Studio), Linux (ARM and x64) and macOS.  We have aPython library wrapping our C code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Talks</title>
      <link>http://roaringbitmap.org/talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://roaringbitmap.org/talks/</guid>
      <description> Engineering Fast Indexes for Big Data Applications, Spark Summit East 2017 (Boston) Engineering Fast Indexes for Big Data Applications (deep dive), Spark Summit East 2017 (Boston)    </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>